Mike Konczal

☑ konczal@gmail.com ③ mikekonczal.com ⑤ mtkonczal ઁ mtkonczal Ť Takoma Park, MD

Professional Summary

Accomplished researcher, writer, and advocate skilled in economic data and policy analysis. I've been cited in over 300 press articles, testified before Congress four times, and made over 50 media appearances on platforms like CBS Sunday Morning and Washington Journal. My written work has been featured in esteemed publications such as The New York Times and The Washington Post.

Experience

Special Assistant to the President for Economic Policy, White House, Washington DC

2024

- Developed strategic arguments for the President's economic policy agenda, in close consultation with colleagues at the Treasury Department and the Council of Economic Advisers.
- Lead the formulation of the White House's messaging following all macroeconomic data releases, including themes, statements, charts, and talking points. Tracked the process for data releases, created internal NEC measures, and directed rapid analysis and response on indicators.
- Provided ongoing analysis for National Economic Advisor Lael Brainard, and support for NEC Deputy Director for fiscal and macro policy, including on tax, budget, and housing policy.
- Amplified the economic messaging of the White House and National Economic Advisor, via speechwriting, social media, and media interaction. Regularly engaged external economic validators, experts, reporters, and academics on both economic data and the President's agenda.

Director, Roosevelt Institute, New York, NY

2010 - 2023

- Directed the macroeconomic research team, providing original research on key economic issues, including inflation, growth, and employment, at a leading think tank. Served as a go-to expert on economic and policy issues for journalists and policymakers.
- Authored regular briefings and white papers on current events to inform strategic decisions and develop talking points. Automated real-time data analysis with R across major data releases. Collaborated with the communications team to devise engagement strategies for our projects.
- Orchestrated four multi-year research and policy initiatives as an expert on topics including the Dodd-Frank Act, the Great Recession, economic inequality, and evolving economic paradigms. Authored over 20 white papers and edited four comprehensive report volumes. Managed teams of two researchers and three external fellows.
- Successfully secured and managed research grants from organizations such as the Kauffman, Ford, and Hewlett Foundations, as well as Open Philanthropy.

Financial Engineer, Moody's KMV, San Francisco, CA

2007 - 2009

- Developed testing benchmarks for Moody's KMV credit risk model, recognized as the 2006 "Top Provider in Trading and Banking" by Risk Magazine. Collaborated on five system releases of RiskFrontier software, developing test cases and acceptance criteria for cutting-edge credit risk modeling algorithms.
- Actively participated in discussions on various approaches to credit risk modeling, focusing on the Vasicek-Kealhofer (VK) model derived from the Black-Scholes-Merton framework. Contributed to debates on capital requirements and loss reserving.

• Prototyped research algorithms using R, SAS, Matlab, and Excel VB to replicate results. Designed and implemented a system that automated the collection, storage, and analysis of significant data sets across four releases, reducing test execution time by 40 percent.

Senior Test Engineer, Motorola, Schaumburg, IL

2001-2005

• Directed performance, load, and stress testing across four major iDEN system releases, earning a Motorola BRAVO Award for "above and beyond performance contribution." Designed automated Six Sigma-level test cases using Perl, Python, and MySQL based on models of consumer behavior. Trained six employees in testing methods.

Education

M.S. Finance, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

2007

- Completed coursework in the graduate-level economics sequence, covering microeconomics, macroeconomics, and econometrics.
- Conducted advanced research in finance, including research replication on large datasets like Compustat, using R and SAS. Modeled option valuation using binomial tree, Monte Carlo, and finite difference methods in C++.

B.A. Mathematics and Computer Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

2001

 Focused coursework in Probability, Statistics, Data Structures, Graph Theory, Numerical Methods, and Nonlinear Programming.

Media Appearances and Writings

Quotes and Media Mentions

- Highly experienced in media engagement, cited in over 300 articles and media references.
- Top Outlets: New York Times (32), Washington Post (23), Vox (21), Bloomberg (10), Business Insider (9), and more.

Published Writing

- Contributed articles to many publications, including but not limited to: *The Nation* (19 articles), *Dissent* (7), *Vox* (6), *Boston Review* (5), and the *New York Times* (2).
- Published the book *Freedom From the Market* (New Press, 2021), highlighted as a "Summer Book of 2021" in the economics category by the *Financial Times*. Reviews include: *Democracy Journal, Foreign Policy, Foreign Affairs, Wall Street Journal*, and *National Review*.
- Co-authored *Rewriting the Rules of the American Economy* (W.W. Norton, 2015), with Nobel laureate Joseph Stiglitz, summarizing the latest research in inequality.

Media Appearances

- Garnered significant media presence with over 25 podcast appearances and 15 TV interviews, and amassed a following of over 50,000 on Twitter.
- Notable Appearances: *The Weeds* podcast (4 times), *Planet Money* (3), *Washington Journal* (2), *CNBC* (2), *CBS Sunday Morning*, and *The Rachel Maddow Show*.

Full C.V. available upon request.